Guide to the Leonard H. Clark military history collection, 1942-1968
George Mason University Libraries
Special Collections and Archives, George Mason University
Leonard H. Clark military history collection
1938-2003
George Mason University. Special Collections and Archives
Leonard H. Clark, 1919-2003
C0060
2 linear feet (4 boxes)
The collection contains documents, photographs, and memorabilia related to Major Clark's service in the United States Air Force. Most notably, the collection contains military records, Japanese souvenirs from World War II, and aerial photographs made by Clark of military operations in the Philippines. The collection contains material from 1938-1968 and 2003.
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
There are no access restrictions.
Acquisition Information
Donated by Susan Lanson in 2008, on behalf of Anna Mae Clark, Robin Clark, and Barbara Clark Gregg.
Biographical Information
Leonard H. Clark was born in England in 1919 and served in the United States Air Force from 1941 to 1968. During World War II, Clark began his service as a test pilot and was assigned to the 43rd Bomb Group of the 403rd Bomb Squadron in the 5th Air Force. In 1944, Clark assumed command of the 403rd Bomb Squadron. In total, Clark participated in 73 combat missions against Japanese forces in the Pacific Theater. Tokyo Rose nicknamed the 403rd the "Mareeba Butchers," the only nickname bestowed by the Japanese propaganda broadcast on a military service group. In 1945, Clark was involved in a plane crash off the cost of Japan, breaking his leg and waiting six days for rescue. During the war, Clark was promoted to the rank of Major and awarded multiple commendations and awards, including the Distinguished Unit Badge and the Distinguished Flying Cross. During the Korean War, Clark served with the 3906th Combat Support Group as a pilot. Clark was again called to serve in the Vietnam War. Major Clark died in Florida in 2003.
Scope and Content
The collection contains the military service and medical records of Leonard H. Clark, his correspondence, photographs, and memorabilia from Leonard H. Clark's service in the United States military. Robert Mathias, a relative of Clark's, gave him photographs and papers that document his time as a member of the United States Navy during World War II. The collection also contains materials in Japanese and Arabic. The collection is arranged into four series and covers a period from 1938 to 2003.
Series 1 contains the documents from the collection, including training logs, service records, medical documents, and correspondence. The series also contains documentation regarding awards and commendations, as well as newspaper clippings. The series covers the period from 1938 to 1968 and 2003 and is arranged in 1.5 boxes.
Series 2 contains photographs from Clark's military service. The series contains personal photographs, as well as publicity photographs of training exercises and aerial photographs of military operations in the Philippines. The series covers the period from the 1940s to the 1960s and is contained in 2 boxes.
Series 3 contains the miscellaneous memorabilia of the collection. Notably, the series contains a collection of currency collected during and after World War II, maps of portions of the Pacific Theater of Operations, and souvenirs from various locations around the world. The series also contains Clark's Distinguished Flying Cross. The series covers the period from the 1940s to 1957 and is contained in 2 boxes.
Series 4 contains the oversized materials from the collection, such as oversized silk maps, a Japanese flag belonging to a Kamikaze pilot, and a scrapbook. The scrapbook contains military training photographs, nose art photographs, Japanese surrender photographs, and newspaper clippings of Clark's training and service in World War II. The scrapbook is particularly interesting because of the documentation of a single squadron. Additionally, the scrapbook contains satirical drawings made during the war. The series covers the period of the 1940s and is contained in 1 box and the oversized map cases.
Arrangement
The collection is arranged in 4 series:
Series 1: Documents, 1938-1968, 2003 (Boxes 1-2)
Series 2: Photographs, 1940s-1960s (Boxes 2, 4)
Series 3: Memorabilia, 1940s-1957 (Boxes 2-3)
Series 4: Maps/Oversize, 1940s (Box 4, Oversize Map Cases)
Adjunct Descriptive Data
Related Material
Special Collections and Archives also holds the, which contains entertainment materials written by and for the United States military during and immediately following World War II.
More information about the 43rd Bombing Group and the 403rd Squadron can be found on the. More information about the Distinguished Flying Cross can be found on the.
Index Terms
Persons:
Clark, Leonard H., 1919-2003.
Corporate Names:
United States. Air Force.; United States. Army Air Forces. Bomb Group, 43rd.
Geographical Names:
Philippines--History--Japanese occupation, 1942-1945.
Subjects:
World War, 1939-1945--Pacific Area.
Contents List
- Series 1: Documents, 1938-1968, 2003
  Series 1 contains the documents of the collection, including service records, flight logs, medical records, and correspondence. Additionally, the series contains documents concerning Robert Mathias, a relative of Leonard H. Clark. The series is contained in 1.5 boxes. The series covers the time period from 1938-1968, with some materials from 2003.
  - Aircrew Standardization/Evaluation Records, 1967-1968 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Biographical Information/Obituary, 2003 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Citations and Awards, 1938-1968 (Box 1, Folder 3)
    Contains a photograph concerning one of the citations.
  - Correspondence, 1941-1945 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Correspondence/Military, 1945 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Documents, 1941-1967 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Documents, 1941-1968 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Evaluations, 1953-1968 (Box 1, Folder 8)
    Contains a photograph from Leonard Clark's military records.
  - Flight Logs, 1942-1963 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Flight Training, 1953-1960 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Miscellaneous Clippings, 1944-1967 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Orders, 1944-1958 (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Personnel Records, 1940-1953 (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - Robert Martin Mathias Documents, 1946 (Box 2, Folder 2)
    This folder contains documents relating to Robert Mathias, a relative of Leonard Clark's and a sailor on the USS Boston. The materials in this folder accompany the Robert Mathias photographs in Series 2.
  - Veterans' Benefits, 1960s (Box 2, Folder 3)
- Series 2: Photographs, 1940s-1960s
  Series 2 contains the photographs of the collection. Notably, the series contains aerial photographs from combat operations, as well as photographs linked to the Robert Mathias documents. The series is contained in 2 boxes and covers the period from the 1940s to the 1960s.
  - Aerial Photographs, 1943-1944 (Box 2, Folder 4)
    Aerial observation photographs of air operations in the Philippines, particularly of operations around Rabaul.
  - Aircraft Photographs, 1950s-1960s (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - Photographs, 1940s (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - Robert Martin Mathias Photographs, 1940s (Box 2, Folder 7)
    This folder contains photographs of Robert Mathias and is associated with the Robert Mathias documents in Series 1.
  - Oversized Aerial Photographs, 1940s (Box 4)
    Aerial observation photographs made by Clark of air operations in the Philippines, particularly of operations around Rabaul.
- Series 3: Memorabilia, 1940s-1957
  Series 3 contains the various items and souvenirs collected by Clark during his tenure in the military, including global currency, Japanese souvenirs, and his Distinguished Flying Cross. The series is contained in 2 boxes and contains material from the 1940s to 1957.
  - Air Force Base Guides/Souvenirs, 1941-1954 (Box 2, Folder 8)
  - Identification Cards, 1940s (Box 2, Folder 9)
  - Insignia, 1940s (Box 2, Folder 10)
  - Japanese Propaganda, 1940s (Box 2, Folder 11)
  - Sidi Slimani Air Base, Morocco, 1957 (Box 2, Folder 12)
  - World Currency, World War II, 1943-1944 (Box 2, Folder 13)
  - Distinguished Flying Cross, 1944 (Box 3)
- Series 4: Maps/Oversized, 1940s
  Series 4 contains the oversized materials from the collection. Notably, the series contains a Japanese flag, silk maps, and a scrapbook. The series is contained in one box and in a folder labeled "Clark Collection" in the "Miscellaneous" map case drawer. The series contains material from the 1940s.
  - Maps/Oversized, 1940s (Oversize MC)
    Contains oversized silk maps used by Clark and a Japanese flag with writing. The flag was labelled as a Kamikaze pilot's sash.
  - Scrapbook, 1940s (Oversize 4)
    Contains photographs, newspaper clippings, and drawings concerning Leonard Clark's service in World War II.